<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Polisci on If You Care</title>
    <link>http://tylerdavis.info/categories/polisci/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Polisci on If You Care</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2015 13:52:06 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://tylerdavis.info/categories/polisci/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Democracy in America</title>
      <link>http://tylerdavis.info/post/democracy-in-america/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2015 13:52:06 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tylerdavis.info/post/democracy-in-america/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;this-is-an-essay-that-i-wrote-when-i-have-more-time-i-will-elaborate-more-on-my-stance-and-take-out-the-essayness:507f84182d69c5ebcf490990adb9a307&#34;&gt;This is an essay that I wrote. When I have more time I will elaborate more on my stance and take out the essayness.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Dahl and the Constitution&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the proposal of the American Constitution in 1787, there have been debates on whether or not the Constitution is sufficiently democratic. Two of the strongest arguments have come from James Madison and Robert Dahl. Although Madison’s beliefs and writings differed throughout his life, his most influential writings came from when he was vying for the ratification of the Constitution. Madison’s beliefs were directly influenced by the previous governments he had lived under. One government had too much central power and the other was limited to a fault. A republic became the only viable option. Unfortunately, since no successful republics previously existed, he had no historical education on the subject to draw from, forcing Madison into basing some of his policy making purely on theory and idealism.  Dahl, on the other hand, lived in the twentieth century and had access to hundreds of years of carefully studied republic histories and was able to analyze the benefits and pitfalls of each of the different republics throughout the world. Dahl’s position that the Constitution should be more democratic is correct because he was able to see the pitfalls of Madison’s system. This is demonstrated by Dahl’s strong argument for majority rule and Madison’s weak argument for strong checks and balances contained within the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Madison was particularly worried about factions. Madison describes a faction as, “a number of citizens … who are united and actuated by some common impulse … adversed to the rights of other citizens.” To control the effects of the factions, Madison proposed a large republic represented by the elect. The elect would be people who would, “refine and enlarge the public views,” “best discern the true interest of their country,” and not be easily corrupted. The elect would not always be selected directly by the people but would instead, in some cases, be elected by other branches of the government or by electors, thus isolating the government from the whims of the masses. On the matter of an isolated government, Dahl said that the “undemocratic aspects that were more or less deliberately built into the constitution overestimated the dangers of popular majorities.” Dahl believed that more trust should be given to the people as a whole, the government should be more democratic with leaders directly elected by the people, and that many of the safeguards put in place by the framers of the constitution did more harm than good, even by the framers standpoints. Dahl says of the electors,  “In an outcome the Framers had made possible by their defective design of the electoral college, the election of 1800 produced a tie … shifts and abstentions by a number of state delegations gave Jefferson the presidency … Ironically, the very institution that the Framers hoped would insulate the election of the president from partisan politics was its first victim.” In this example, Dahl explains how the Electoral College that was designed to be isolated from the people gave way to delegations, falling victim to partisan politics. This is one of the many ways that the ‘padding’ between the government and the people has failed to do what is was designed to do. This padding has failed in other ways, such as causing people not to vote because their voice may be drowned out by the electors, or removing potential ‘elect’  who would “best discern the true interest of their country” from the system simply because they don’t have the means or influence to run for office. A more democratic system would better represent the voice of the people and give them a greater sense of inclusion (Madison #10; Dahl pg 39, 30).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ambition must be made to counteract ambition,” is one of Madison’s famous quotes. Madison lobbied for three branches of the government. Each branch of government had some sort of influence over the other branches to leverage them. In this way, each of the branches could keep the other branches in check. If one branch went in the wrong direction, the other branches could pull them back in, thus counteracting their ambition. The problem with this system stems somewhat from the isolation of the people. The Judiciary branch has been given the power to declare any law unconstitutional, nullifying that law, but the people have no influence over that branch. The Judiciary branch can silence the people. For example, Proposition 8 in California’s November 2008 ballot, was passed by a majority vote but then struck down by the Court. Millions of people were left stunned. Their voice had been heard, the law had been set in place, and then a handful of people had flattened it. Dahl would say that this is undemocratic and goes against an ideal government. This type of action leads  to an ununited people that long for a more equal say in the laws that affect their everyday lives. No single person or small group of people should have such unchecked power over millions of others (Madison #51).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Madison had some inspired ideas, his theories were incorrect in some areas and the safeguards that he put in place to protect the people from themselves failed in some aspects. Dahl recognized many of Madison’s inspired ideas but realized where the government fell short. Dahl realized that only a more democratic system would truly capture the voice of the people and lead to a system that empowered the idea that “all men are created equal”. Therefore, the Constitution should be more democratic than it is today (Declaration of Independence. 1776).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Madison, James (1787). &amp;ldquo;Federalist #10&amp;rdquo; in The Federalist Papers, ed. Clinton Rossiter New York Daily Advertiser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Madison, James (1787). &amp;ldquo;Federalist #51&amp;rdquo; in The Federalist Papers, ed. Clinton Rossiter New York Daily Advertiser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dahl, R. (2001). How democratic is the American Constitution? New Haven: Yale University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>